so welcome to our lecture where we start talking about the speed, clock speed, how circuits have delay
in the previous lecture we introduced for the first time the notion of a clock and that is
a value that is at zero and then when we want something to happen we set it to one and when we're done we set it back to zero
now this is a circuit it's a combinatoric circuit and
if you play with this online you'll see that it you change a number and it takes a little bit of time for the
propagation to end up at the output of this circuit
and that's just because it's kind of slow in my online emulator this is a full adder circuit and
this is not a very long circuit but you can see over time how these are going to get longer especially
when we start chaining them right so if we make a four bit adder that's
four full adders where the carry out goes to the carry in
the carry out of the second one goes to carry into the third and the carry out of the third one goes to the fourth
now those values will only settle down after the carries have propagated all the way down that chain and that's just a four bit adder
you could have a 32 bit adder or a 64 bit adder or even a multiplier in hardware and so the
the propagation through a 64 bit multiplier is going to take a little while
and so these circuits get more complex than what we've done
but when they build them they'll make a 64 bit adder it takes two operands and produces a result
and the designers of the chip hardware will simulate and simulate and tweak it and simulate and simulate it
how long is it that if you present inputs to a 64 bit adder until the outputs are reliable and no longer changing
and that's called the clock rate and if we take a microprocessor
we compute the delay of the slowest element or longest path in the arithmetic and logic unit
we can determine the number of times per second we can reliably do computations
and then we set the clock rate to be a little conservative okay
and so this is another example of the intel 4004 which is our favorite little first widely available commercial microprocessor
and so as microprocessors have gotten smaller as the width of each wire and with the transistors have gotten smaller
you can make the distances between the transistors smaller
as we went to CMOS and we could manage heat better we could put things more tightly packed
the more tightly packed we do the faster they go and so this is a graph of a thing called Moore's law
and it was something that people just started seeing once we would improve the technology
then we would build microprocessors with that new technology then we improve the architecture of those microprocessors
and then we would do new technology it turned out that the number of integrated circuits
and pretty much for a while the clock speed of them would double about every two years
so how do we know what the clock rate is like I mentioned the size of the chip because when we're doing things this fast the speed of light matters
the number of transistors because each transistor takes a little while to flip as you change its input and its output needs to change
the physical length of any long path and just because a chip is one inch wide doesn't mean there's not paths that are several inches
because they go round and go back and forth and the speed at which transistors switch and this depends on the technology and it gets better over time
and like I said these chips are laid out and simulated endlessly during development to figure out how we can take this chip
and then you've probably heard about people overclocking their chips and that's when someone changes the clock
because they think that the factory was being too conservative on the clock rate so let's add 10% and see if it starts blowing up
and that's called overclocking so let's play with a simple circuit
we're going to take two of the circuits that we built in previous lectures and combine them together
so what we're going to do is we're going to take an adder and a clock and a register
so the adder simply takes two 3-bit numbers from 0 through 7 on the A 1s 2s and 4s for the A and 1s 2s and 4s for the B
and so we have our two operands we have our sum values which are the sum and they are copied to the input values of our latch
and we have a clock on the latch because if you recall while the clock is low we don't care about the input changes
so right now our adder is 0 we are adding 0 plus 0 and getting 0 our latch is still a 0
not because the adder is 0 but because the clock is 0 and the latch was 0 before
if we change the input on the adder we are going to do a 2 plus 4 A is 2 B is 4 and the adder now has produced it
there's a delay there but you'll notice the latch hasn't changed because we haven't pressed the clock yet
the clock is still at 0 and the definition of the clock in a latch is that the latch is ignoring its input change
any changes on input until the clock goes 1 so when the clock goes 1 the sum values are latched into the latch memory
now if you keep the clock 1 and fiddle with the inputs of the adder then you're not sure what's happening
because it may take a while to go through the adder or it might come through very quickly
but the smart thing to do is then set the clock back to 0 because we have the sum copied from the adder
and now we can change the inputs right once we have the clock at 0 we can just feed different inputs into the adder
so now we're adding 4 plus 3 now the clock is still 0 and we have changed the inputs to the adder
we are now adding 4 plus 3 what the adder is reflecting the sum as soon as we change those inputs right
the adder just as a combinatoric circuit takes its inputs produces the output
but because the clock is still 0 the clock is low the latch hasn't accepted those values yet right
when the clock goes high the 7 is going to be copied into the new latch value
now if we do this you can build this circuit with my little circuit emulator
you can build the circuit where you have the adder you have a latch
and you can interactively play with the ones twos and fours for both the A input and the B input
but instead of having a button for the clock we have a programmable clock
and the clock object goes from 0 to 1 back to 0 every second
so what happens is you can fiddle with the inputs of this see how fast you can change them
and every second whatever is in the adder is going to be copied into the latch
now we're going to go a little farther in the next lecture with what we're doing with clocks and gates and adders and latches